<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.30 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-kuehlewind-quic-manageability-00" category="info">

  <front>
    <title>Manageability of the QUIC Transport Protocol</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Kuehlewind" fullname="Mirja Kuehlewind">
      <organization>ETH Zurich</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gloriastrasse 35</street>
          <city>8092 Zurich</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mirja.kuehlewind@tik.ee.ethz.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Trammell" fullname="Brian Trammell">
      <organization>ETH Zurich</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gloriastrasse 35</street>
          <city>8092 Zurich</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ietf@trammell.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Druta" fullname="Dan Druta">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dd5826@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017" month="June" day="06"/>

    
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document discusses manageability of the QUIC transport protocol, focusing
on caveats impacting network operations involving QUIC traffic. Its intended
audience is network operators, as well as content providers that rely on the use
of QUIC-aware middleboxes, e.g. for load balancing.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>QUIC <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-transport"/> is a new transport protocol currently under
development in the IETF quic working group, focusing on support of semantics as
needed for HTTP/2 <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-http"/>. Based on current deployment practices, QUIC is
encapsulated in UDP and encrypted by default. The current version of QUIC
integrates TLS <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-tls"/>
to encrypt all payload data and most control information. Given QUIC is an
end-to-end transport protocol, all information in the protocol header, even that
which can be inspected, is is not meant to be mutable by the network, and will
therefore be integrity-protected to the extent possible.</t>

<t>This document provides guidance for network operation on the management of QUIC
traffic. This includes guidance on how to interpret and utilize information that
is exposed by QUIC to the network as well as explaining requirement and
assumptions that the QUIC protocol design takes toward the expected network
treatment. It also discusses how common network management practices will be
impacted by QUIC.</t>

<t>Of course, network management is not a one-size-fits-all endeavour: practices
considered necessary or even mandatory within enterprise networks with certain
compliance requirements, for example, would be impermissible on other networks
without those requirements. This document therefore does not make any specific
recommendations as to which practices should or should not be applied; for each
practice, it describes what is and is not possible with the QUIC transport
protocol as defined.</t>

<t>QUIC is at the moment very much a moving target. This document refers the state
of the QUIC working group drafts as well as to changes under discussion, via
issues and pull requests in GitHub current as of the time of writing.</t>

<section anchor="notational-conventions" title="Notational Conventions">

<t>The words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “SHOULD”, and “MAY” are used in this document.
It’s not shouting; when these words are capitalized, they have a special meaning
as defined in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="features-of-the-quic-wire-image" title="Features of the QUIC Wire Image">

<t>In this section, we discusses those aspects of the QUIC transport protocol that
have an impact on the design and operation of devices that forward QUIC packets.
Here, we are concerned primarily with QUIC’s unencrypted wire image, which we
define as the information available in the packet header in each QUIC packet,
and the dynamics of that information. Since QUIC is a versioned protocol,
also the wire image of the header format can change. However, at least 
the mechanism by which a receiver can determine which version is used and the
meaning and location of fields used in the version negotiation process need to be fixed.</t>

<t>This document is focused on the protocol as presently defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-transport"/> and
<xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-tls"/>, and will change to track those documents.</t>

<section anchor="public-header" title="QUIC Packet Header Structure">

<t>The QUIC packet header is under active development; see section 5 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-transport"/> for the present header structure.</t>

<t>The first bit of the QUIC header indicates the present of a long header that exposes more information than 
the short header. The long header is typically used during connection start or for other control processes while the short header will be used on most data packets to limited unnecessary header overhead. The fields and location of these fields as defined by the current version of QUIC for the long header are fixed for all future version as well. However, note that future versions of QUIC may provide additional fields. In the current version of quic the long header for all header types has a fixed length, containing, besides the Header Form bit, a 7-bit header Type, a 64-bit Connection ID, a 32-bit Packet Number, and a 32-bit Version. The short header is variable length where bits after the Header Form bit indicate the present on the Connection ID, and the length of the packet number.</t>

<t>The following information may be exposed in the packet header:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>header type: the long header has a 7-bit header type field following the Header Form bit. The current version of QUIC defines 7 header types, namely Version Negotiation, Client Initial, Server Stateless Retry, Server Cleartext, Client Cleartext, 0-RTT Protected, 1-RTT Protected (key phase 0), 1-RTT Protected (key phase 1), and Public Reset.</t>
  <t>connection ID: The connection ID is always present on the long and optionally
present on the short header indicated by the Connection ID Flag. If present at
the short header it at the same position then for the long header. The
position and length pf the congestion ID itself as well as the Connection ID
flag in the short header is fixed for all versions of QUIC. The connection ID
identifies the connection associated with a QUIC packet, for load-balancing
and NAT rebinding purposes; see <xref target="loadbalancing"/> and <xref target="rebinding"/>.
Therefore it is also expected that the Connection ID will either be present on
all packets of a flow or none of the short header packets. However, this field
is under endpoint control and there is protocol mechanism that hinders the
sending endpoint to revise its decision about exposing the Connection ID at
any time during the connection.</t>
  <t>packet number: Every packet has an associated packet number. The packet number increases with each packet, and the least-significant bits of the packet number are present on each packet. In the short header the length of the exposed packet number field is defined by the (short) header type and can either be 8, 16, or 32 bits. See <xref target="packetnumber"/>.</t>
  <t>version number: The version number is present on the long headers and identifies the version used for that packet, expect for the Version negotiation packet. The version negotiation packet is fixed for all version of QUIC and contains a lit of versions that is supported by the sender. However the version in the version field of the header is the reflected version of the clients initial packet and is therefore explicitly not supported by the sender.</t>
  <t>key phase: The short header further has a Key Phase flag that is used by the endpoint identify the right key that was used to encrypt the packet. Different key phases are indicated with the use of the long header by using to different header types for protected long header packets.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="wire-integrity" title="Integrity Protection of the Wire Image">

<t>As soon as the cryptographic context is established, 
all information in the QUIC header, including those exposed in the packet header, is
integrity protected. Further, information that were sent and exposed in previous packets 
when the cryptographic context was established yet, e.g. for the cryptographic initial handshake itself,
will be validate later during the cryptographic handshake, such as the version number.
Therefore, devices on path MUST NOT change any information or bits in QUIC packet
headers. As alteration of header information would cause packet drop due to a
failed integrity check at the receiver, or can even lead to connection termination.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="rebinding" title="Connection ID and Rebinding">

<t>The connection ID in the QUIC packer header is used to allow routing of QUIC
packets at load balancers on other than five-tuple information, ensuring that
related flows are appropriately balanced together; and to allow rebinding of a
connection after one of the endpoint’s addresses changes - usually the client’s,
in the case of the HTTP binding. The connection ID is proposed by the server
during connection establishment, and a server might provide additional
connection IDs that can the used by the client at any time during the
connection. Therefore if a flow changes one of its IP addresses it may keep the
same connection ID, or the connection ID may also change together with the IP
address migration, avoiding linkability; see section 7.6 of
<xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-transport"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="packetnumber" title="Packet Numbers">

<t>The packet number field is always present in the QUIC packet header. The packet
number exposes the least significant 32, 16, or 8 bits of an internal packet
counter per flow direction that increments with each packet sent. This packet
counter is initialized with a random 31-bit initial value at the start of a
connection.</t>

<t>Unlike TCP sequence numbers, this packet number increases with every packet,
including those containing only acknowledgment or other control information.
Indeed, whether a packet contains user data or only control information is
intentionally left unexposed to the network. The packet number increases with every packet
but they sender may skip packet numbers.</t>

<t>While loss detection in QUIC is based on packet numbers, congestion
control by default provides richer information than vanilla TCP does.
Especially, QUIC does not rely on duplicated ACKs, making it more tolerant of
packet re-ordering.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="initial-handshake-and-pmtud" title="Initial Handshake and PMTUD">

<t>[Editor’s note: text needed.]</t>

</section>
<section anchor="version-negotiation-and-greasing" title="Version Negotiation and Greasing">

<t>Version negotiation is not protected, given the used protection mechanism can change with the version.
However, the choices provided in the list of version in the Version Negotiation packet will be validated
as soon as the cryptographic context has been established. Therefore any manipulation of this list
will be detected and will cause the endpoints to terminate the connection.</t>

<t>Also note that the list of versions in the Version Negotiation packet may contain reserved versions. This mechanism is
used to avoid ossification in the implementation on the selection mechanism. Further, a client may send a Initial Client packet with a reserved version number to trigger version negotiation. In the Version Negotiation packet the connection ID and packet number of the Client Initial packet are reflected to provide a proof of return-routability. Therefore changing these information will also cause the connection to fail.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="specific-network-management-tasks" title="Specific Network Management Tasks">

<t>In this section, we address specific network management and measurement
techniques and how QUIC’s design impacts them.</t>

<section anchor="statefulness" title="Stateful Treatment of QUIC Traffic">

<t>Stateful network devices such as firewalls use exposed header information to
support state setup and tear-down. <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness"/> provides a
general model for in-network state management on these devices, independent of
transport protocol. Features already present in QUIC may be used for state
maintenance in this model. Here, there are two important goals: distinguishing
valid QUIC connection establishment from other traffic, in order to establish
state; and determining the end of a QUIC connection, in order to tear that state
down.</t>

<t>Both, 1-RTT and O-RTT connection establishment, using a TLS handshake on stream 0, is detectable
using heuristics similar to those used to detect TLS over TCP. 0-RTT connection
may additional also send data packets, right after the client hello. These data may be
reorder in the network, therefore it may be possible that 0-RTT Protected data packet are 
seen before the Client Initial packet.</t>

<t>Exposure of connection shutdown is currently under discussion; see
https://github.com/quicwg/base-drafts/issues/353 and
https://github.com/quicwg/base-drafts/pull/20.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="measurement" title="Measurement of QUIC Traffic">

<t>Passive measurement of TCP performance parameters is commonly deployed in access
and enterprise networks to aid troubleshooting and performance monitoring
without requiring the generation of active measurement traffic.</t>

<t>The presence of packet numbers on all QUIC packets allows the trivial one-sided
estimation of packet loss and reordering between the sender and a given
observation point. However, since retransmissions are not identifiable as such,
loss between an observation point and the receiver cannot be reliably estimated.</t>

<t>The lack of any acknowledgement information or timestamping information in the
QUIC packet header makes running passive estimation of latency via round trip
time (RTT) impossible. RTT can only be measured at connection establishment
time, by observing the Client Initial packet and the Server’s reply to this packet which
maybe a Server Cleartext, Version Negotiation, or Server Stateless Retry packet.</t>

<t>Note that adding a packet number echo (as in
https://github.com/quicwg/base-drafts/pull/367 or
https://github.com/quicwg/base-drafts/pull/368) to the public header would allow
passive RTT measurement at on-path observation points. For efficiency purposes,
this packet number echo need not be carried on every packet, and could be made
optional, allowing endpoints to make a measurability/efficiency tradeoff; see
section 4 of <xref target="IPIM"/>. Note further that this facility would have significantly
better measurability characteristics than sequence-acknowledgement-based RTT
measurement currently available in TCP on typical asymmetric flows, as adequate
samples will be available in both directions, and packet number echo would be
decoupled from the underlying acknowledgment machinery; see e.g. <xref target="Ding2015"/></t>

<t>Note in-network devices can inspect and correlate connection IDs for partial
tracking of mobility events.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ddos-detection-and-mitigation" title="DDoS Detection and Mitigation">

<t>For enterprises and network operators one of the biggest management challenges
is dealing with Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attacks. Some network
operators offer Security as a Service (SaaS) solutions that detect attacks by
monitoring, analyzing and filtering traffic. These approaches generally utilize
network flow data <xref target="RFC7011"/>. If any flows pose a threat, usually they are
routed to a “scrubbing environment” where the traffic is filtered, allowing the
remaining “good” traffic to continue to the customer environment.</t>

<t>This type of DDoS mitigation is fundamentally based on tracking state for flows
(see <xref target="statefulness"/>) that have receiver confirmation and a proof of return-routability, 
and classifying flows as legitimate or DoS traffic. The
QUIC packet header currently does not support an explicit mechanism to 
easily distinguish legitimate QUIC traffic from other UDP traffic. However,
the first packet in a QUIC connection will usually be a Client Initial packet. 
This can be used to identify the first packet of the connection.</t>

<t>If the QUIC handshake was not observed by the defense system, 
the connection ID can be used as a confirmation signal as per
<xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness"/> if present in both directions.</t>

<t>Further, the use of a connection ID to support connection migration renders
5-tuple based filtering insufficient, and requires more state to be maintained by
DDoS defense systems. However, it is questionable if connection migrations needs to be
supported in a DDOS attack. If the connection migration is not visible to the network 
that performs the DDoS detection, an active, migrated QUIC connection may be blocked 
by such a system under attack. However, a defense system might simply rely on the fast
resumption mechanism provided by QUIC. This problem is also related to these issues under 
discussion: https://github.com/quicwg/base-drafts/issues/203</t>

</section>
<section anchor="qos-support-and-ecmp" title="QoS support and ECMP">

<t>QUIC does not provide any additional information on requirements on Quality of Service (QoS)
provided from the network. QUIC assumes that all packets with the same 5-tuple 
{dest addr, source addr, protocol, dest port, source port} will receive similar network treatment.
That means all stream that are multiplexed over the same QUIC connection require the 
same network treatment and are handled by the same congestion controller. If 
differential network treatment is desired, multiple QUIC connection to the same server might
be used, given that establishing a new connection using 0-RTT support is cheap and fast.</t>

<t>QoS mechanisms in the network MAY also use the connection ID for service differentiation 
as usually a change of connection ID is bind to a change of address which anyway is likely to
lead to a re-route on a different path with different network characteristics.</t>

<t>Given that QUIC is more tolerant of packet re-ordering than TCP (see <xref target="packetnumber"/>), 
Equal-cost multi-path routing (ECMP) does not necessarily need to be flow based. 
However, 5-tuple (plus eventually connection ID if present) 
matching is still beneficial for QoS given all packets are handled by the same
congestion controller.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="loadbalancing" title="Load Balancing using the Connection ID">

<t>The Connection ID is used in part to support load balancing in content
distribution networks (CDNs), which operate complex, geographically distributed
pools of back-end servers, fronted by load balancing systems.  These load
balancers are responsible for identifying the most appropriate server for each
connection and for routing all packets belonging to that connection to the
chosen server.</t>

<t>Load balancers are often deployed in pools for redundancy and load sharing. For
high availability, it is important that when packets belonging to a flow start
to arrive at a different load balancer in the load balancer pool, the packets
continue to be forwarded to the original server in the server pool.</t>

<t>Support for seamless connection migration is an important design goal of QUIC
– a necessity due to the proliferation of mobile connected devices. This
connection persistence provides an additional challenge for multi-homed
anycast-based services often employed by large content owners and CDNs. The
challenge is that a migration to a different network in the middle of the
connection greatly increases the chances of the packets routed to a different
anycast point of presence (POP) due to the new network’s different connectivity
and Internet peering arrangements. The load balancer in the new POP, potentially
thousands of miles away, will not have information about the established flow
and would not be able to route it back to the original POP.</t>

<t>Load balancers may cooperate with servers or server pools behind them to use a
server-generated Connection ID value, in order to support stateless load
balancing, even across NAT rebinding or other address change events (see
<xref target="rebinding"/>). See section 5.7 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-transport"/>.</t>

<t>Server-generated Connection IDs must not encode any information other that that
needed to route packets to the appropriate backend server(s): typically the
identity of the backend server or pool of servers, if the data-center’s load
balancing system keeps “local” state of all flows itself.  Care must be
exercised to ensure that the information encoded in the Connection ID is not
sufficient to identify unique end users. Note that by encoding routing
information in the Connection ID, load balancers open up a new attack vector
that allows bad actors to direct traffic at a specific backend server or pool.
It is therefore recommended that Server-Generated Connection ID includes a
cryptographic MAC that the load balancer pool server are able to identify and
discard packets featuring an invalid MAC.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>Supporting manageability of QUIC traffic inherently involves tradeoffs with the
confidentiality of QUIC’s control information; this entire document is therefore
security-relevant.</t>

<t>Some of the properties of the QUIC header used in network management are
irrelevant to application-layer protocol operation and/or user privacy. For
example, packet number exposure (and echo, as proposed in this document), as
well as connection establishment exposure for 1-RTT establishment, make no
additional information about user traffic available to devices on path.</t>

<t>At the other extreme, supporting current traffic classification methods that
operate through the deep packet inspection (DPI) of application-layer headers
are directly antithetical to QUIC’s goal to provide confidentiality to its
application-layer protocol(s); in these cases, alternatives must be found.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="contributors" title="Contributors">

<t>Igor Lubashev contributed text to <xref target="loadbalancing"/> on the use of the connection
ID for load balancing.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">

<t>This work is partially supported by the European Commission under Horizon 2020
grant agreement no. 688421 Measurement and Architecture for a Middleboxed
Internet (MAMI), and by the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research,
and Innovation under contract no. 15.0268. This support does not imply
endorsement.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>





<reference  anchor='RFC2119' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-quic-transport'>
<front>
<title>QUIC: A UDP-Based Multiplexed and Secure Transport</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Iyengar' fullname='Janardhan Iyengar'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Thomson' fullname='Martin Thomson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='21' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>This document defines the core of the QUIC transport protocol.  This document describes connection establishment, packet format, multiplexing and reliability.  Accompanying documents describe the cryptographic handshake and loss detection.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-quic-transport-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-quic-transport-03.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-quic-tls'>
<front>
<title>Using Transport Layer Security (TLS) to Secure QUIC</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Thomson' fullname='Martin Thomson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S' surname='Turner' fullname='Sean Turner'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='21' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>This document describes how Transport Layer Security (TLS) is used to secure QUIC.  Note to Readers  Discussion of this draft takes place on the QUIC working group mailing list (quic@ietf.org), which is archived at https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/search/?email_list=quic .  Working Group information can be found at https://github.com/quicwg ; source code and issues list for this draft can be found at https://github.com/quicwg/base-drafts/labels/tls .</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-quic-tls-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-quic-tls-03.txt' />
</reference>




    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference  anchor='RFC7011' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7011'>
<front>
<title>Specification of the IP Flow Information Export (IPFIX) Protocol for the Exchange of Flow Information</title>
<author initials='B.' surname='Claise' fullname='B. Claise' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Trammell' fullname='B. Trammell' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Aitken' fullname='P. Aitken'><organization /></author>
<date year='2013' month='September' />
<abstract><t>This document specifies the IP Flow Information Export (IPFIX) protocol, which serves as a means for transmitting Traffic Flow information over the network.  In order to transmit Traffic Flow information from an Exporting Process to a Collecting Process, a common representation of flow data and a standard means of communicating them are required.  This document describes how the IPFIX Data and Template Records are carried over a number of transport protocols from an IPFIX Exporting Process to an IPFIX Collecting Process.  This document obsoletes RFC 5101.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='77'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7011'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7011'/>
</reference>


<reference anchor="IPIM" >
  <front>
    <title>In-Protocol Internet Measurement (arXiv preprint 1612.02902)</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Allman">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Beverly">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Trammell">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016" month="December" day="09"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="Ding2015" >
  <front>
    <title>TCP Stretch Acknowledgments and Timestamps - Findings and Impliciations for Passive RTT Measurement (ACM Computer Communication Review)</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Ding">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Rabinovich">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2015" month="July"/>
  </front>
</reference>




<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-quic-http'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) over QUIC</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Bishop' fullname='Mike Bishop'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='May' day='21' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>The QUIC transport protocol has several features that are desirable in a transport for HTTP, such as stream multiplexing, per-stream flow control, and low-latency connection establishment.  This document describes a mapping of HTTP semantics over QUIC.  This document also identifies HTTP/2 features that are subsumed by QUIC, and describes how HTTP/2 extensions can be ported to QUIC.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-quic-http-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-quic-http-03.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness'>
<front>
<title>Transport-Independent Path Layer State Management</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Kuehlewind' fullname='Mirja Kuehlewind'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Trammell' fullname='Brian Trammell'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Hildebrand' fullname='Joe Hildebrand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='28' year='2017' />

<abstract><t>This document describes a simple state machine for stateful network devices on a path between two endpoints to associate state with traffic traversing them on a per-flow basis, as well as abstract signaling mechanisms for driving the state machine.  This state machine is intended to replace the de-facto use of the TCP state machine or incomplete forms thereof by stateful network devices in a transport-independent way, while still allowing for fast state timeout of non-established or undesirable flows.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-trammell-plus-statefulness-03' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-trammell-plus-statefulness-03.txt' />
</reference>




    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>

